Hi, in this module I'll introduce you to
several ways to select, retrieve, and sort
data with Pandas. After watching this
module, you'll be able to retrieve exactly
the subset of data you need from any
Pandas DataFrame. Usually there are
several different ways to accomplish this,
and I will compare and contrast those for
you. Most of this module is about
indexing, which is the primary way to get
to your data. There's a lot to say about
indexing, because Pandas offers many
powerful options there. I'll start by
covering the basics of the indexing
operator and what happens when you pass a
single value to it to select a single row
or column. Next we'll see what happens
when you index a DataFrame with a more
complex data structure like a list or
slice, and we'll see two DataFrame
attributes called loc and iloc, which
allow us to index in even more powerful
ways. Then we'll move on to Boolean
filtering, selecting data using a
comparison like all rows that have a value
higher than x, for example. We'll see that
you can assign values to the part of a
DataFrame that you select when you use an
index, and finally, I have a short word
about sorting. Let's start with a demo
about indexing. I'll start with the
basics, selecting single rows and columns,
and we'll gradually move towards more
complex use cases like indexing with
slices, lists, and indexing with loc and iloc.