I've started a new notebook, and you see
the familiar imports. I'm reading the same
csv file as before, and I'm getting the
first five rows only by calling the
function head on it before assigning it to
the variable df. This way we have a small
and simple dataset to work with for our
demo. In a sense, a DataFrame is nothing
more than a list of series containing
values, and an index that gives each of
these series a name, and each series is
one of the columns we see here, like Time,
Temp or Pressure. So the most
straightforward thing we can do with a
DataFrame is to select one of these
columns, and we can do that with straight
brackets and the name of the column we
want, like this. And this selects a series
of temperatures from this dataset. Of
course, when I use a name that doesn't
exist I get an error. But let's assume we
use an existing column and we retrieve a
series. On this series we can now call
methods like max or min, or we can select
a single value from the series by using
the same operator again, but this time on
the series itself. Since the first part of
the expression here evaluates to a series,
we can put another subscript behind it,
and that will work on that series. So to
get the second temperature, which has
index 1, I add square brackets 1. Now
before I go into a little more detail
here, there's something you should know.
What you see in a lot of tutorials and
examples is that people leave out the
brackets when selecting a column, which
looks like this, which, as you can see,
selects the same series. Now if you know
about Python classes and objects, you will
know that this is a syntax for retrieving
an attribute from a Python object. For our
convenience, DataFrame has an attribute
for each of its columns, but this will
only work when the name of the column is a
valid Python attribute name. To put it
simply, this will not work when the column
name has spaces or certain special
characters like an equals or plus sign, or
a dot, and you can also not add a new
column with this syntax, which is possible
with the brackets, and we'll see that
later. So for all of these reasons, in my
opinion it is better not to use this
syntax, or at least don't use it in any
production code. It's just not a best
practice, even if it's shorter to type.
Let's talk a bit more about simple
indexing. For my next example, I'm going
to transpose our DataFrame with the. T
attribute and assign that to a new
variable df. T, and let's see what that
looks like. So in this case the names of
my columns are integers, and the row index
contains strings. Let's see if indexing
still works the same way. Using the same
approach as before with brackets and
quotes doesn't work, and that's because
the quotes here create a string asking the
DataFrame for a column associated with a
string 2. But our column names right now
are actually integers, and you can check
this by asking for the attribute dft.
columns. And this tells us that the
columns are indexed by a range of numbers
from 0 to 4, so this means that to
retrieve column 2 we need to remove the
quotes. And now we retrieve the series we
want. So to retrieve a column we have to
use exactly the kind of value that's in
the column index. In this case, it's a
number and that means we can also not use
the dot syntax. This isn't even valid
Python code. Now interestingly, for series
this works differently. Once I have a
series, like here where I retrieve the
column with index 2, I can retrieve a row
from that series by a value that's in its
index, so in this case let's get the Time
for column 2. Let me just remove the other
cells here to make things clear again. And
similarly, in this case, I can use the
index of the row I want to retrieve, since
the row for Time is the third row so it
has offset 2, and as you can see, I can
retrieve it by position as well as by
name. Now the subtly here is that you can
retrieve rows from a series both by
position and by name, but you can retrieve
columns only by label. Scrolling back up,
we see that we retrieved columns by their
index label. Temp is the name of the
column as it occurs in the index in the
first example, and if you try to retrieve
this column with its position, 3, because
it's the fourth column and we start
counting with 0, you would find that it
doesn't work, so you can retrieve this
column by its name, but not by its
position. And in the other example back
down, here we are retrieving a column with
a number, but that only works because in
this case the column index also contains
numbers. Once we have extracted a series
from the DataFrame, though, like we would
get column 2 here, then we have a series
and we can retrieve rows from that series,
both by label and position. So you see
here that we retrieved the Time row both
by saying Time and by saying I want row 2.
Well, actually what I'm saying isn't
completely correct, you can retrieve
columns by position as well, and we'll see
that in a moment. Now let me give you a
final strange example. Consider the
following DataFrame. In this case we have
rows indexed with numbers, but the numbers
are not a simple range. As you can see,
there are even multiple rows with the same
index. Now in this case my earlier comment
is not true. Here you can only retrieve
rows by name. Now my question to you is
what do you think will happen if I get the
series with values like this and then
select row 4 like this? The answer I leave
to you. I encourage you to play around in
the notebook and figure this one out for yourself.