So we've seen what happens when we put a
single value between these brackets like a
number or a string, but we can use more
complicated things in here as well, like
for example, a list of column names. And
this returns a DataFrame with the columns
I selected. As you can see, the columns
can be in any order, regardless of the
order in which they appeared in the
original DataFrame. Similarly, when I
select a single series I can use the same
logic on that series to select a number of
rows. Now note that in both cases here we
have double square brackets. The outer
brackets mean we are indexing into the
DataFrame of our series, and the inner
brackets mean that we're using a Python
list to select multiple things at once.
Another thing we can pass to the indexing
operator is a slice. You may know this
from Python. A slice a uses a colon to
select a range of things. So far, we've
used indexing to select columns from a
DataFrame, but with a slice you always
select rows, and this expression means
we're selecting rows 2 up to, but not
including 4, so that means rows 2 and 3.
Because this returns a DataFrame, I can
select which columns I want immediately
after this, so let's use the double square
brackets to select the temperature and
pressure at these two rows. Now if we look
at our transposed DataFrame, let's try to
get exactly the same data points from this
data structure. Again, indexing with a
slice will always select rows, so here to
select pressure and temperature let's say
3 followed by a column, which means I want
a range of all rows starting from the
fourth row, which is offset 3 up until the
very last row. Again, this returns a
DataFrame, so if we want to select columns
2 and 3 from this we cannot use a slice,
because that always selects rows, but I
can use a list to select multiple columns.
So let's use double square brackets, and
now we have the same data as above, only
transposed. Now if you select only a
single row like this, we now have a
series, and here, again, we can also use
slicing, and again, a slice always selects
rows, so I can say column 4 to select only
the first four rows. Even in the case of
our transposed data structure where the
row indices are strings, slicing works,
and it selects rows. And we can even use
slicing with strings. So in this example
I'm selecting the rows Time up until
Pressure. Note that in this case the end
of the slice is inclusive, so the Pressure
row is included in the results, whereas
with integer slices the endpoint of the slice is not included in the results.