So with the regular indexing operator on a
DataFrame, you can select one or more
columns. But what if you want to select
just a row or several rows? We've seen
that you can use slicing, but there are
several other possibilities that we
haven't seen yet. Before I start, let's
make a new DataFrame to play with. This
time I will create a DataFrame using
Python data structures. You can type along
if you like, or you can download the
notebook from the course materials. What
we have here is a list of some of the
smallest capital cities in the world. I'm
creating a DataFrame by calling pd.
DataFrame, and I pass the list of cities
as a list of lists. So these outer
brackets contain five lists, and each of
those lists is a row containing the data
for a city. For example, we see that the
country of Tuvalu has a capital city
called Funafuti with about 4. 5 thousand
inhabitants, making up 45% of the total
population of the country. As a second
argument, I'm passing a list of countries
which will become the row index, and I'm
giving an argument columns where I set the
name of the columns, which is also a list.
So now when I say capitals, this is what
our data looks like. Now I want to
introduce two other ways to retrieve data
from this DataFrame. First of all, there's
the loc attribute, which allows us to do
row-based indexing as opposed to
column-based indexing which you've seen in
the previous clips. In this case, I also
use square brackets, and I start with
selecting a row, let's say Nauru. And here
loc allows me to immediately select a
column as well, inside the brackets. So
let's ask for the population of the
capital of Nauru by typing a comma and
population within quotes. Now remember
that to retrieve the same data from the
DataFrame with column-based indexing, we
have to first select the Population column
and then drill down into the row for
Nauru. And this is called chained
indexing, and it takes two operations,
where the line with loc only takes a
single operation, and for this reason the
use of loc is usually preferred over
chained indexing, and I'll get back to
this point in a moment. Both arguments of
loc also support lists and slices, so for
example, here I use a slice to select the
rows for Palau up to Nauru, and the list
to select two specific rows. Of course,
you can also use a list as the first
argument and the slice as the second.
Please take a moment to try and verify for
yourself that this works. And, again, you
can do this with column-based indexing as
well, but it will take two separate steps,
where this is a single operation. Now by
the way, you can also leave out the second
argument altogether. So in this example
I'm using capitals. loc to quickly get the
rows for San Marino and the Vatican. Now
one thing you should realize is that loc
only indexes by label, not by position. To
retrieve items by position, we use another
attribute called iloc. It works in a
similar way, we start by selecting one or
more rows, but this time we use integers
to denote the positions of the rows we
want. And, again, we can add a second
argument here to select columns. I can
select all columns except the first by
using a slice that starts at 1. Now with
iloc, indexing is strictly location based.
So even if you have an integer index and
there is no row with index 4, or the
indices are not nicely ordered, this line
of code will always select the fifth row
and the second row. Now as a final
example, let me show you, you can do
something with iloc which you cannot do
with the column-based indexing from
previous clips. It allows us to select a
column by position. Let me show you. I
start by selecting all rows by using only
a colon, which is a slice that selects the
whole range, and then I can select column
2 for example. So loc and iloc allow you
to select rows, columns, and even single
cells with a single operation. You can use
two arguments. The first one selects rows
and the second one selects columns, and
the big difference between the two is that
loc uses labels and iloc uses positions.
In other words, it uses integers to denote
the position of a row or column. With loc,
of course, you can also use integers, but
only if your actual index labels are integers.