So the most straightforward thing you can
do with indexing is to pass a column
label, which will retrieve the column from
the DataFrame as a series. Note that there
has to be a column with that index label
in the DataFrame, so in the second example
here we are retrieving a column with label
5, not the column with position 5. To do
that, we need to use iloc. Once you
retrieve a column, you can use indexing on
that to retrieve one or more of its
values, and we call this chained indexing.
If you need to select multiple columns at
once, you can use indexing with a list.
note that we have double square brackets
in the example here. The outer ones are
for the indexing operator, and the inner
ones are for the list. And this way you
can retrieve any number of columns in any
order you like. You can also use a slice,
and this behaves differently in the sense
that it always selects rows instead of
columns. With slices you can select by
position or by name, and it both works.
And, by the way, you can use lists and
slices with all kinds of indexing, so you
can use them with loc and iloc, on Series
and DataFrame, and it all works. The
DataFrame has an attribute called loc
which allows for row-based indexing. In
the example here, we retrieve the row with
label San Marino. If you also want to
select the column you want to see, you can
pass it a second argument. So with loc you
can drill down to a single cell in a
single operation. By the way, both
arguments can be lists or slices as well,
so you can select multiple rows or columns
here. Now if you compare this to
column-based indexing, you see that we
first select a column and then the row,
and we need two operations for this. And
this is slightly less efficient, and in
fact, using loc is usually preferred. I'll
get back to this in a moment. Then there's
iloc, which also does row-based indexing,
but it works by position, whereas loc
works by label. So with iloc I can pass an
integer to retrieve a single row, and in
this case it will retrieve the sixth row
because, of course, we start counting at
0. Iloc also lets us select the column in
the same operation. Again, this will
select by position, so we're getting the
third column, and like I've said before,
you can use slices and lists as arguments both with loc and iloc.