In the second part of this module, I want
to move on from just indexing. First I'd
like to take a look at filtering data
using Boolean expressions, then we'll see
that we can assign new values to the parts
of our DataFrame that we have selected
with the techniques we have learned so
far, and I'll finish up the module by
taking a short look at sorting. As you
already know, passing a list to the index
operator on our DataFrame we can select
columns from our data. So here I'm
selecting the capital names with their
population. But there's another kind of
list we can also use. Let me show you. I
can pass a list of Booleans, and this list
selects only some rows from our data. The
list has to have as many elements as there
are rows, so in this case I need five
elements, and for every row in the data I
say whether I want it in my output. So
here I'm selecting the first two rows,
skipping the third, selecting the fourth,
etc. Now you may wonder what's the point
of this. If my data contains 200, 000
rows, I'm not going to type 200, 000 times
true or false. Well, the beautiful thing
is that we can generate lists of Booleans.
Let's say I want to see only the rows
where the capital city contains more than
a quarter of all the population in the
country. To start, I select the Percentage
column, and remember this expression will
return a series containing only the
percentages, and now I can compare a
series to a single value. So let's say is
greater than 25, and this returns a series
with Booleans, telling me for every row
whether the percentage in that row is
greater than 25. And because this
expression returns a list, I can use it in
an indexing operation like this. So let me
explain the syntax another time. Selecting
the Percentage column returns a series.
Comparing this with a value returns a
series of Booleans which you can use to
index your DataFrame, so this will return
exactly the rows where the percentage is
greater than 25. Now just to make a point,
let me add another DataFrame and it
contains a number of student names and
their grades on two different tests. Now
suppose I want to select those students
whose score didn't improve after the first
test. I can actually compare two columns
against each other like this, and this,
again, returns a series with Booleans,
which I can use inside an indexing
operation. So this shows me exactly the
students who didn't improve. You can also
use these Boolean expressions with loc and
iloc. For example, I might want to see
only the tests that have an average over
5. 5, and this means I want to create a
list of Booleans that has the same length
as the number of columns in my data. First
I will calculate the averages, and this
already creates a series, so all I have to
do is to compare this with 5. 5 and now we
have a series of Booleans, and I can plug
this into loc like this. So here I use a
colon as the first argument, which means I
want to see all rows, and as a second
argument I pass my Boolean list, which
selects only the first column because
that's the only test with an average over 5. 5.