So far, all of this module has been about
retrieving data, but in this clip I want
to talk for a short moment about changing
data. You see, almost all of the indexing
operations return a view on the original
DataFrame, and you can assign values to
that. Let's say I made an error in marking
test 2, and both John and Laura deserve
better grades. I can select their marks
using loc, and then I can increase their
scores with 1 by using += 1. Checking the
contents of the DataFrame, we see that the
grades have been updated. I can even
upgrade an entire column at a time. Let's
increase the grade on the first test, or
for a specific student. So these indexing
operations don't return new data, but a
view on the original DataFrame allowing us
to update it. You can also pass multiple
values, so let me just set the grades for
Pete, and passing a list updates multiple
grades at once. You can even use
assignment with the Boolean filters we've
seen before. Let's convert the values we
have right now into a string saying Pass
or Fail. First I select all grades smaller
than 6 and set them to the string Fail,
and then I take everything larger than 6
and covert those to Pass. Surprisingly,
this converts everything to Pass, and
that's because after the first line we
have a DataFrame holding both numbers and
strings, and comparing the strings to the
number 6 in the next line always yields
true, so we convert everything to the
string Pass. Now one way to fix this is to
first store the Boolean arrays in a
variable. Remember that these expressions,
grades smaller than 6 and grades larger
than 6, return series of Booleans, so I
can assign these series of Booleans to
variables, and then I can use these
variables inside the square brackets. Of
course, right now this is not going to
work because I already changed all my data
into strings. So let's rerun the whole
notebook from the start, and now we have
the result we want. Now, of course, this
is kind of a silly example, so let's make
it a bit more realistic. I'll start by
recreating the original data, because I
want to leave the code above for you to
read. So a more common scenario for a
teacher is to take the average for each
student, not for each test, so we want an
average by row. But the mean method, by
default, takes averages per column.
Fortunately, we can add an argument, axis,
and set it to 1, which means we want to
average all of the rows, and this returns
a series containing the averages per
student. Now let's convert this to
Booleans by saying greater than 6, and
this gives us a series of Booleans. And we
can actually add this data as a column to
our DataFrame by simply using the name of
new column for an index. So here I'm
creating a new column and assigning it a
Boolean value denoting whether this
student passed. Now looking at the data,
you can see that this column has now been
added. So indexing also allows the
creation of new columns. Sometimes when
you make a mistake this also causes the
creation of a new column. For example, I
want to set Ann's grade on test 2 to an 8,
but I forgot to use loc. Now this indexing
operation is nonsense. We cannot pass a
column and a row like this, so instead
Pandas assumes I want to create a new
column. Looking at the results, you see
that there's now a new column that we
didn't mean to create at all. We've
already seen that one way to do this uses
loc, but you might also try to do this
without loc, selecting first the column
and then the row with two different index
operations. But this gives a warning.
Checking grades, we see that the statement
has been successfully executed, so what
went wrong here? Well, using multiple
index operations after each other is
called chained indexing, and if you use
those and try to assign a value to it,
Pandas cannot guarantee that it will work,
so in these cases it's better to use loc
because that's more likely to work and
it's faster anyway. Now you might wonder
when exactly an indexing operation returns
a view on the original data that we can
safely assign to. Well, to quote the
Pandas documentation, outside of simple
cases, it's very hard to predict whether
indexing will return a view or a copy, and
that's exactly why Pandas gives the
warning above, to let you know when you
are in a situation where assignment may not work exactly the way you expect it.