To wrap up the module, let's talk about
sorting for a moment. There are two
methods you need to be aware of. First
there's sort_index, which, as the name
implies, sorts by index. So I can say
capitals. sort_index, and I get a new
DataFrame sorted by index, which in this
case means we sort by country names. By
default, this method does not change the
original DataFrame, so that means if we
check capitals it's still unsorted. If you
need the original data to be sorted, use
inplace=True, and now the capitals
variable itself is sorted. You can also do
a reverse sort by saying ascending is
False. And you can also sort by the column
index. To do so we add the argument axis
is 1, so now our data is sorted in
descending order along the row index and
in ascending order along the column index.
But, of course, sometimes you don't want
to sort by index of your data, but by
value. For this there is the method
sort_values. And if you run it without any
arguments you get an error, because you
need to supply it an argument so that it
knows by which column to sort, so we can
say we want to sort it by the Percentage
column. Sometimes you need a secondary
column to sort by. As an example, let's
sort our grades. And here I'm passing a
list of columns to sort by. The primary
sort column is test_1, but students who
received the same score on that test, for
example, Mary and Pete who both received a
6, are sorted by test_2. By the way,
sort_values also supports the other
arguments we've seen like inplace,
ascending, and axis. As always, I suggest
you take a moment and play around with
these methods to verify that this works
the way you expect it to. And that brings
us to the end of our demos for this module. Let's review.