We've seen that we can use Boolean
comparisons to select parts of our data by
using the comparison inside the indexing
operation. The example you see here
selects all rows from a DataFrame where
the column called Temp has a value greater
than 20. Note that we have two pairs of
square brackets, one to select the column
and another one that accepts the Boolean
expression and selects matching rows. The
name of our DataFrame, df, also appears
twice. Now this works because the
comparison of a series with a number
returns a new series with Booleans, so
comparing the Temperature column with the
number 20 returns a Boolean series and we
can use that inside square brackets to
retrieve matching rows. You can also use
this with other ways of indexing like loc
and iloc, and here I have an example where
I first pass a colon, which is a slice
that selects everything. So this first
argument selects all rows, and then the
second argument is a list of Booleans. In
this case we select columns, and that
means that the list must contain as many
Booleans as there are columns. Well,
grades. mean returns a mean for every
column, and comparing that to the number 6
returns a list of Booleans. Most of the
time using an indexing operation with
Pandas returns a view on the original
DataFrame, and that means you can assign
values to the selected part of your data.
In the first example here I'm I'm
selecting a column and increasing every
value in it by 1, and the second example
selects a row and sets its values using a
list. This tends to work with all indexing
operations, so it also works with loc and
iloc. In this example, I'm selecting two
cells by using loc and selecting a row and
two columns, and I'm setting both values
to 8. You may have noticed that I was
using uncertain wording with the previous
slide. This is because I cannot give you
certainty that these Pandas operations
always return views. The Pandas
documentation is quite clear on the
uncertainty here. They cannot give any
guarantees, and this is especially true in
the case of chained indexing, like you see
in the example here. I'm first indexing a
DataFrame which returns a series, and then
I'm indexing that series. When I try to
assign a value to that, I get a
SettingWithCopyWarning, and this means
that Pandas cannot tell you whether you're
assigning to a view of your original data
or to a copy. So, did the assignment work?
I don't know, it depends. The best thing
to do is test the result of your code, and
in general you will usually see this
warning when you use chained indexing, so
try not to do that when you assign values,
instead use loc and iloc because those
usually work. We also saw two methods for
sorting your data. First there's
sort_index, which as the name implies,
sorts your data by the index, and the
other one is sort_values, which sorts on
the actual values of your data. In this
case you need to specify which column of
your DataFrame to sort by. If necessary,
you can also select multiple columns to
sort on. There's a number of extra
arguments that you can pass to the sort
methods. First of all, there's the
ascending option, which makes Pandas sort
in reverse when it's set to false. Then
there's the axis argument, which you can
set to 1 if you want to sort along rows
instead of columns. Actually, there are a
lot of methods that take this argument. In
the demo, we've also seen it, for example,
with the mean method. And usually sorting
with Pandas does not change the data
itself, but it will return a sorted copy.
If you want to change the original
DataFrame, pass the argument inplace=True.
By the way, all of these arguments work
with both sort_index and sort_values. And
that's it for this module. We've learned a
lot about indexing from the basics of
retrieving single rows and columns to
indexing with slices and lists and doing
row-based indexing with loc and iloc. We
saw Boolean filtering, which is a powerful
way to select parts of your data based on
logical expressions, assigned new values
to our data, and took a short look at
sorting methods. Thank you for watching,
and I hope that you'll join me in the next
module where we'll talk about cleaning your dataset with Pandas.