Hi everyone, my name is Reindert-Jan
Ekker, and welcome to this playbook about
manipulating data with Pandas. I'm a
senior developer and freelance educator,
and in this course I'll teach you about
Pandas, the most popular Python framework
for doing data science and analysis. The
role of Pandas in data analysis has been
growing hard over the past few years, and
you simply cannot go without Pandas
anymore. This course goes over the core
tasks that you will need to perform when
working with any real-world dataset, and
we'll do so in a very hands-on way. Some
of the major topics that we will cover
include exploring a new dataset;
selecting, sorting, and filtering your
data so that you can drill down into your
dataset to answer specific questions;
cleaning a dataset, which means doing
things like fixing bad or missing data
points and removing outliers; and
transforming your data either by doing
calculations on it, or by changing the
structure of your dataset. By the end of
this course, you'll have a good
understanding of the core functionality of
a Pandas DataFrame, and you'll be able to
handle most everyday tasks. Before
beginning the course, you should be
familiar with the very basics of Python
and data science. I hope you'll join me on
this journey to learn how to manipulate
your data with Pandas with the Pandas
Playbook: Manipulating Data at Pluralsight.