Hi, in this module we'll look at the first
steps for a data scientist when working
with new datasets, exploring it to get a
feeling for the kind of data we have, the
statistical properties it has, and more.
Whenever you start to work with a new
dataset, the first thing you normally want
to do is to explore what the data looks
like. How many items are there in the set,
and what kind of measurements are there?
To get a feeling for the dataset, you
usually also want to see a quick overview
of basic statistics like the mean, max,
and minimum values, etc., etc., and maybe
even make a few simple plots while you're
at it. So this is exactly what I'll do in
this module. I'll show you how to get up and running with a new dataset.