So now let's start off with a short demo.
We'll look at some of the core Pandas
features that we can use to get a first
impression of the contents of a new
dataset, including the number of rows and
columns and their data types, as well as a
preview of the actual data itself. I've
started a Jupyter Notebook and navigated
to the directory where I keep the data for
this course. All files I use will be
available to download, so here you can see
a file called weather. csv, which I have
prepared so that it's really easy to read
with Pandas. So starting a notebook here
in this directory, I select Python 3, and
in the new notebook let's start by setting
the title and calling it Exploring a
dataset. Then I start the notebook by
loading the essentials I always need. I
import numpy as np, pandas as pd, and I
say matplotlib inline, which enables us to
view graphical output in the notebook.
Then I press Shift+Enter to execute the
cell. Next let's read the weather data
from the file. To do so, I call the pd.
read_csv method with the name of the
weather. csv file. I make a new variable,
df, which is short for DataFrame, and in
there I store the data from csv. Now I've
taken care to make it so that weather. csv
contains data that we can read with this
simple function call. In real-world
situations, reading your data will
probably be slightly more complicated, but
for now I'm going to ignore that and just
assume that you're getting your data
loaded into a pandas DataFrame
successfully. Let's go ahead and see what
this DataFrame looks like. I might start
by saying df. shape, and this is a
property, not a function, and it contains
a tuple telling us the size of the
DataFrame. So now we know that there are
8784 rows and 5 columns to the DataFrame.
But kinds of data are in there? Let's call
df. info. And this function call gives us
a little more information. It tells us
that our df object is of class DataFrame,
it has 5 columns, and it also tells us the
name and type of each column. Now this is
a very clean dataset in the sense that it
doesn't contain any empty or missing
values or errors, and you can see that
reflected in the fact that each column has
a value count of 8784. We have four
integer columns which cannot hold missing
values anyway, and a single floating-point
column. The info method also shows us the
amount of memory occupied by our data, and
the type of index for this DataFrame. In
this case, the index has been added
automatically by Pandas, so we have a
range index which is the default, a range
of numbers from 0 to 8783. Now I also like
to get an impression of what the actual
data looks like. For that, there are two
methods you should know about, head and
tail. As you probably can guess, df. head
shows you the first rows of data.
Executing it, we see that it shows five
rows, but I can optionally add the number
of lines to show as an argument. So let's
change this to 50 here, and now we see the
first 50 lines. In this case, we don't see
anything unexpected. The data does seem to
be sorted by month, day, and hour though.
Let's check the last few rows as well with
df. tail, and this seems to confirm that our data is nicely sorted.