Now that we know the dimensions and type
of our data, let's do a little statistical
exploration. We'll see how to get a
general statistical overview, as well as a
few more specific statistical functions,
and a few basic plots. The next function
we call on our dataset is df. describe,
and this function gives a high-level
overview of our data from a statistical
standpoint. For each column it gives some
basic statistical data, like the mean, the
standard deviation, minimum and maximum
values, and the quartiles. For the first
three columns, which tell us about the
moment that each sample was taken, this
information doesn't make a lot of sense,
but for the last two they do. Apparently
for this weather station, which is located
in the Netherlands, the average
temperature was around 10 degrees Celsius
over the whole year with a standard
deviation of about 6 degrees. Looking at
the quartiles, at first glance it looks
like the temperatures are pretty evenly
distributed around the mean. We can also
see that the Month column is in the range
from 1 to 12, and the Day counts from 1 to
336, which makes sense because this data
is from 2016, which was a leap year so it
has one extra day. By the way, the
behavior of the describe method depends on
the type of data in your DataFrame, so if
you have any columns that don't have just
numbers, but, for example, objects or
categorical types, you will see different
results, and some columns may be ignored
by the describe method altogether. Now you
can get all of the numbers generated by
describe in another way as well, by asking
for them explicitly. To get the mean for
the columns, for example, you call df.
mean, and for the max df. max, etc., etc.
But you can also run these methods against
a single column. For example, to get the
minimum pressure measured, I can say df
followed by square brackets, and in there
I put the name of the column I want to
use, PRESSURE, and then I say. min, and
this returns a single number, which is
nice if I need to store it in a variable
to do calculations with. There's a large
number of things you can calculate in this
way, and it's pointless to show all of
them one by one, so let me show you how to
get sort of an overview of what's
possible. If you click on Help, and then
Pandas Reference, this takes me straight
to the Pandas documentation. And then I
scroll all the way down to the API for the
Series class. And then I have to scroll
even further down to find the part about
Computations/Descriptive Statistics. So
here we see a list of many basic
operations you can do on a Series, and
almost all of these also work on your
entire DataFrame. Here we find, for
example, the count of all observations in
the series, the kurtosis, the max and mean
and median, quantiles, like percentiles
and quartiles, ranks, standard deviation
and variants, the sum of all the values,
etc., etc. So if you want to know what the
most often measured temperature is in this
dataset, which in statistics you would
call the mode, you should be able to find
out that you can call the function mode
for that, because it's in the reference I
just showed you. So we can say df square
brackets, temperature,. mode. Now this
method always returns a Series, even when
there's only a single value, so we see
here that the first value of this Series
is 6. 4, making 6. 4 degrees Celsius the
most often occurring temperature. Finally,
even though this course doesn't focus on
visualization, I want to give you a few
pointers for looking at the data in a
graphical way. Most plotting functionality
is accessed through the. plot attribute of
a DataFrame or Series. To plot all
temperatures, I can say df TEMP. plot, and
this plots all temperatures as they occur
in the series. Or maybe it's more
informative to ask for a histogram by
saying df TEMP. plot. hist. Now such a
histogram you can make more or less fine
grained with the bins parameter, so let's
set bins to 100 and we get a histogram
with 100 bars. Now, of course, there's a
lot more to be said about visualization
and data exploration, but I think this
short demo gives a good first impression of the things Pandas can do.