So, after you load a new dataset into a
Pandas DataFrame, usually you want to do
more or less the following: check the
shape property to get the dimensions of
the data, call the info method to see what
data type each column has, what kind of
index you have and how much space all of
this occupies in memory, call head or tail
to check out what the data itself actually
looks like, and by the way, don't forget
you can pass an argument to tell those
methods how many rows to show, and call
the describe method to get a high-level
overview of important statistics like the
mean, max, and min, etc. A lot of the
time, you may want to go one step further
and check some more specific statistical
properties. Pandas has a lot of common
statistical operations built in, and all
of the functions I mentioned here can be
used both on a series or on a DataFrame.
First of all, there are the max, min,
mean, and median functions. All of these
are also generated by the describe method,
but sometimes you need to generate them
for a specific column, or you may need
them for a calculation. The mode function
tells you the most common value in the
dataset, and will return multiple values
if necessary. There's also a method
value_counts which returns a series with
the number of times each value occurs in
your dataset. But notice, as an exception
this method can only be called on a
Series, so on one of the columns in your
data, not on the entire DataFrame. In some
cases, you want some more information
about the distribution of your data, and
for these cases Pandas offers methods like
std and var for the standard deviation and
variants, or the skew, kurtosis, and
quantile methods, which do exactly what
their name implies. Of course, it's also
quite easy to make the most beautiful and
informative plots and graphs with Pandas,
but I won't go into these much in this
course because we will be focusing mainly
on the DataFrame and Series classes, and
what you can do with them. Now, I only
showed you a very minimal demo of all of
this, and let me take a step back and look
at a realistic scenario. I loaded a
dataset about UFO sightings and called
info on it, and this is what I see. It's a
lot less friendly than what we saw in the
previous demo. The count for the columns
differ a lot, which means that a lot of
columns are missing values. Almost all the
columns are objects, which can mean
several things, but one thing it surely
does not mean is that these columns
contain clean number data. This is
actually a much more realistic example
than what we saw in the demo a moment ago.
In a case like this, we need to clean up
and transform the data, see what to do
with missing or erratic values, and more,
and that's exactly what we will do in this
course. So let's move on to the next
module about selecting, filtering, and sorting data.