Hi, my name is Reindert-Jan Ekker, and
welcome to this course about data
manipulation with Pandas. Pandas is not
just one of the most popular software
packages for data analysis, it's also,
without a doubt, the most convenient and
fun way to work with your data. In this
course, I will cover the most important
core functionalities of Pandas, so that
after watching this course you will be
ready for just about any data wrangling
job that you might come across. In this
short introduction module, I'll tell you
what to expect from this course, what you
should already know, and I'll give you an
overview of the structure of the course.
So, this course focuses on core Pandas
functionality for data manipulation, and
we will look at that functionality in the
context of very common everyday tasks and
problems. Just about all of the
functionality we will explore is made
available through the two main Pandas
classes, the Pandas Series and the Pandas
DataFrame. There's also several things
that you will not find in this course.
Fist of all, this is not a general Pandas
introduction. I will assume a basic
knowledge of what a DataFrame and a Series
are. If you do not know the very basics,
there's a great intro course here on
Pluralsight that you may want to see
first. I'm not going to dive deeply into
data visualization because that's a
completely different topic from the core
data manipulation tasks I want to talk
about in this course. The same is true for
machine learning, or all the various ways
to do input and output with Pandas.
Furthermore, there are some Pandas
features that you may consider important,
or even core features, but that I have
chosen not to cover in this course because
in my opinion they are slightly too
involved. I'm talking about such things as
categoricals, advanced indexing, or time
series. So, what should you already know
before watching this? Well, of course, you
need some basic Python knowledge. At the
very least, you should have an
understanding of the built-in data
structures like lists and dicts, you
should be able to write functions, and you
should have a minimal understanding of
what classes and objects are. You should
also have at least a tiny bit of knowledge
of Pandas. Let's say you have played
around with it a little and you have an
understanding of what a Series, a
DataFrame, and an Index are. Finally,
there's the Jupyter Notebook, which is a
tool I will use to write and run my code.
You should have this installed and
running, and you should know how to work
with Notebook cells, write, edit, and run
code. Now in case this is new for you,
there's a Pluralsight intro course about
Jupyter as well. By the way, my tip to
you, install Anaconda from anaconda. org.
This will install Jupyter, NumPy, and
Pandas, as well as a wealth of other
popular packages for data science and
analysis. In a moment we'll start with the
next module called Exploring Data, and
it's about the first steps you take when
you start working with a new data set. How
much data do you have? What do the rows
and columns look like? We'll also do some
basic statistical exploration of our data.
Then we'll move on to a module called
Selecting, Filtering, and Sorting, and
this module focuses on getting information
out of your data set. Basically, it's
about asking the right questions and
drilling down into your data set. The
third module is about cleaning a data set.
Just about every real-world data set will
have some problems, and this can range
from missing data to unwanted data or
outliers, and we'll see various ways to
deal with those things. And the final
module is about transforming our data. So
here we'll see how to run Python functions
against our data, including functions we
write ourselves, using a very cool and
powerful feature called groupby, changing
the structure of our columns and rows and
combining multiple DataFrames into one.
Very well, that's it for this
introduction. Let's move on to the next module called Exploring data.