Hi, in this module we're going to take a
look at the common ways to clean up your
dataset. When you start working with a new
dataset, usually there are some steps you
want to take to tidy up. In this module, I
will go over some of the more common
scenarios and how to tackle them. To
start, we will see how to investigate
missing data, also called null values, and
we'll see how to detect these values and
take a closer look at them, how to remove
them, and how to replace them with other
values either by replacing all missing
values with a filler, or by interpolating
them from surrounding data. You might also
have some other unwanted data in your
dataset like outliers, or data that occurs
more than once, and of course we'll see
how to handle these as well. And we'll see
how to fix values that don't have the
correct data type, and finally, we'll take
a look at tidying up the index of your DataFrame.