So, let's start off with the first demo,
in which I'll show you how to work with
missing data. First we'll see how to
detect missing values, then how to remove
them, and finally we will learn how to
replace them by other values based on your
actual data. So here we are again in a new
notebook, and we start with the familiar
two imports of pandas and numpy. I'm
reading a csv file again, and it's from
the weather dataset we've seen before,
only this time I haven't cleaned it up
completely. When I call info on it, not
only do we see some extra columns we
didn't see before, there is another
interesting thing you may not notice
immediately. Not all counts for all
columns are the same, and this means that
not all columns contain the same amount of
values. For example, we see that the
MIN_TEMP_GROUND column contains only about
1500 measurements. If you check it, you
will find that it only contains a value
for every six rows. The VIEW_RANGE and
CLOUD columns also have some missing data,
as well as the columns for different
weather types, MIST, RAIN, SNOW, THUNDER,
ICE, and at the end we see the
WEATHER_CODE column and it also has some
missing data. Taking a look at what some
of these columns contain, we see that some
cells here have a value of NaN instead of
a number, and this is an abbreviation for
not a number, and it simply means that
there is no value here, so no
measurements. Basically, there are holes
in our data. Sometimes you want this.
Looking at the MIN_TEMP_GROUND column, the
minimum temperature at ground level is
only recorded once every 6 hours. It's the
minimum temperature measured over that
interval, and the number shows up in the
data at the moment that the measurement
was recorded and the data is left empty at
other moments, so this is not an error. In
the case of the missing WEATHER_CODE, I'm
not so sure where this comes from. It
might mean anything from a measurement
error to an unknown weather type. Let's
take a closer look at the rows and columns
that contain missing values. I can call
df. isnull, and null, by the way, means no
value, and in the Pandas ecosystem null
and not a number are equivalent. This is
not the case everywhere though. In many
languages, not a number and null are two
very different things. Anyway, in this
case the function isnull returns a
DataFrame with True whenever our data is
null and False otherwise. On this
DataFrame I can call any, and this
function takes every column of our
DataFrame and returns True if it contains
any true values at all. So in this case it
shows True for every column that has null
values, and that's quite a lot of columns.
Again, df. isnull is a new DataFrame that
contains True for every null value and
False for everything else. And the
function any works similar to, for
example, the mean function. It computes a
value for every column in the data. In the
case of any, it returns True if there is
any true value in the column. Like we've
seen before, we can give arguments to say
that we want to work over the other axis,
so over the rows instead of the columns.
And now we have a True value for every row
in our data that has one or more null
values. And because this is a list of
Booleans, we can use it to select these
rows and look at them. Right now, all we
can tell from this is that most of the
null values are in the MIN_TEMP_GROUND
column. We'll fix that soon. For now, I
wonder if there are any rows that only
contain null values. Again, I'll start by
saying df. isnull, but this time instead
of any I'll use the all function, and in
this case we get an overview of all
elements of our DataFrame where all values
are True. In the case of the columns, we
already know that every column contains
some data at least, so all columns return
False. To do the same for all rows, again,
I say axis is 1, and I get a very long
list telling me for every row in our data
whether it is completely empty or not. I
would like to know if there are any True
values in this list, so of course I can
say any again. So now we know for sure
that every row in our data contains at
least one value. Explaining the syntax
here once here, df. isnull is a DataFrame
that's True for every null value, and for
every row in that DataFrame we check
whether it's all true values by saying all
with axis is 1. So now we have a series of
True and False value. Calling any on that
Series tells us whether it contains any
True values, which it doesn't, so we know
if we don't have any rows that are
completely empty. Now, there's another
function called notnull which does exactly
the opposite from isnull. It returns True
for every value that is not null. So to
get all columns that have no values at
all, I can say df. notnull. all. Now let's
take it one step further. The column that
has by far the most missing values is the
minimum ground temperature, and by simply
looking at the data it seems that every
sixth value is a number. And actually,
this is also what the meteorological
institute says. This temperature is only
recorded every 6 hours. But let's not just
trust what we hear, let's check that it's
true. So how do I check that every sixth
value is true? Well, let's start by making
a list of all positions in the column
where I suspect there should be a number.
So this uses the standard Python function,
range, generating a list of numbers
starting with 5, which is the position of
the first number in our column, up to the
length of the DataFrame with a step size
of 6. To get a nice overview of what we
just created, I can make this into a
Pandas Series. And this shows us that the
first number is 5, then 11, then 17, etc.,
etc., and scrolling down to the bottom we
see that there are 1464 numbers in this
list. By the way, making this a Series is
not actually necessary, I just did it to
quickly display the contents of our list.
Now, let's store this in a variable called
every_6th_row. And you might remember that
we can use a list of indices to retrieve
rows from our data, so let's take the
MIN_TEMP_GROUND column and index it with
our list of positions. So this will select
exactly every sixth row from this column.
To check that these cells all contain a
measurement, I say. notnull. all, and this
returns True, so now I know that all these
rows are filled. Now to be completely
certain of the way this column is filled,
let's check the opposite. Are all other
rows empty? Again, I select the column,
but now I remove every sixth row by using
the method drop. Now the drop method does
not work in place by default, so our
original DataFrame will stay intact, so
we're not actually removing anything form
our DataFrame. Now these values should all
be null, so I can say isnull. all. And,
again, we get the answer True. So now I
know for sure that this column contains a
value every sixth row, and not a number
everywhere else. Good. Now I would like to
ask you to take a moment and see if you
can rewrite the previous line to use loc instead of chained indexing.