Let's begin cleaning up our dataset. I'll
start by completely removing the weather
type column because that one contains
coded values that are useless to me. I can
remove a column by calling drop on our
DataFrame, and by default drop removes
rows, so I should specify that I want to
remove a column. And here I always run
into the same pitfall. Actually the
argument is not called column but columns,
even if you only want to drop one column.
So let's fix this, very well, and this
gives a new DataFrame without the
WEATHER_CODE column. The fact that we see
a new DataFrame here might tell you
something. The original DataFrame hasn't
been changed. To actually drop the column
from our original DataFrame, we add the
familiar inplace parameter which we've
already used with other methods. Now the
most straightforward approach to dealing
with missing values is to just remove
them. Now in many cases this is not
actually necessary because most
calculations and plots handle null values
in the way you probably want them to.
Taking the mean, for example, simply
calculates the mean from the data points
that are actually there, ignoring any null
values, so you might just be completely
okay with null values in your datasets.
Now in case of the MIN_GROUND_TEMP, I only
have a value once every six rows, and
removing all rows with null value is not
an option at all. But I may want to fill
in this data with something else. Pandas
offers a function to do this for us called
fillna. The simple way to use it is to
just provide a value, let's say 0, and
this fills every missing value with 0.
Now, of course, this is not actually what
I want in this case, I want to fill the
missing entries based on the actual
measurements. Fortunately, fillna can also
do this by saying method is ffill, which
stands for forward fill, and Pandas will
take each measurement and fill the empty
slots after it. You can see the result
here. Each measurement is repeated six
times. Only the thing is that the
measurements are taken over the previous 6
hours, and as a result our first five
cells are still empty, so we actually want
to fill backwards. For this we can use
bfill. Very well. This looks better. Let's
add the parameter inplace is True to
update our DataFrame with these values.
And let's check for the columns with null
values again, and now it tells us that the
MIN_TEMP_GROUND column doesn't have any
null values anymore. So that's nice, we
seem to be about halfway done, because
almost half of our columns are now False
here. And as a side note, in case you need
more sophisticated interpolation of your
values, instead of just copying a value
across a number of missing values, there's
also the interpolate method. And the
interpolate method will do all kinds of
interpolation. I encourage you to try out
this method on the MIN_GROUND_TEMP and see
what kind of results you get. Now let's go
back to the notebook and let's inspect the
missing values we still have left in our
data. Remember, we can get the rows with
missing values by using the same
expression we already have, but specifying
the other axis, and we can use that to
select the actual data by putting it
inside square brackets. And this shows us
the rows with missing values we have left.
Scrolling to the right a bit, we see that
most of the time all the values are
missing in the last seven columns. Now to
look at the date where this occurs I can
use indexing with loc, and this selects
only the dates from these rows, and I'm
going to say. value_counts. And now we see
that there are three days in August where
there are null values for a large part of
the day, and to me this looks like there
were technical problems at the weather
station at that time. So let's just assume
that for my data science project I need
temperature, pressure, and weather types,
so these rows will now be useless to me
because they are missing for large parts
of the date. And I see two possible
solutions. Either remove this data or try
to fill it in some way. Now let's start
with the first one. To simply drop all
rows that contain null values, we say df.
dropna. Now I don't want to do this
inplace because I want to show another
approach in a moment, so I don't want to
mess up my data. Instead I wail save the
output from this command into a new
variable called nulls_dropped. So this
variable will contain a new DataFrame
where all the rows with null values have
been dropped. And calling info on it now
shows that all columns have the same count
of non-null values, but note that the
index still goes from 0 to 8783. So the
side effect of this approach is that now
our data isn't nicely continuous anymore.
If I ask for rows 5300 to 5310, we can see
here that the index is discontinuous. It
jumps from 5305 to 5318, because that is
where we just removed some rows. You can
also see that the row with position 5306
now has index 5318, which is kind of
weird. We'll see how to fix this later.
Now a very useful option with dropna is
thresh. It allows me to determine how many
values must be present in a row to keep it
in my dataset. So here, again, I have the
original dataset df and I call dropna on
it, but I say that I want to drop only
those rows that have less than seven
measurements in them, and then I use
isnull and any to inspect the rows with
null values. And as you can see, now we
have only two rows left, and only the last
five columns are null. Now these are
weather types and contain only 1 or a 0
depending on what is observed, so you
could, for example, use fillna to fill
these cells with zeros. Please take a
moment to try this for yourself. Now,
again, in this case we've dropped some
rows and our index will not be continuous
anymore. So let's take a look at another
approach, which is to fill in our missing
data instead of dropping it. I haven't
used an inplace parameter, so our original
DataFrame, df, is still intact. The
expression to select all rows with null
values should by now be familiar.
Remember, this returns a series of
Booleans, which is true for any row with
null values. Let me just store this in a
variable, rows_to_fill, and you can use it
immediately to look at the rows in
question. These are exactly the rows we
were dropping from the DataFrame a moment
ago. Now a very common approach here is to
fill the empty cells with some kind of
statistical estimate of what the value
might be, like the mean of the column.
Remember, we can calculate the mean of
each column with df. mean, and I can
simply pass this to fillna to use these
mean values instead of the missing cells.
And let's store this in a variable again.
Now, of course, I want to see what the
affected rows look like, but I cannot ask
nulls_filled for its rows which used to be
null. Luckily, I stored these rows in a
variable, rows_to_fill. Okay, so this
looks nice, but now the last six rows
don't contain zeros and ones, but some
floating points, and that's not what I
want. So in the cases of VIEW_RANGE and
CLOUD I'm okay with those rows having a
mean value, but in case of MIST, RAIN,
SNOW, THUNDER, and ICE I just want to see
ones and zeros. So in this case it might
be better to use the mode instead of the
mean, and the mode of our data is the most
occurring value. Now there is a trick to
using it though, and we can read it in the
documentation of the mode method. And here
is a line that actually shows us exactly
how to call mode with fillna. So let's
copy this line and put it in the notebook,
and now we can see that our data has been
filled in quite nicely. So at this point
I'm satisfied, and I want to store this
result back in the original DataFrame. So
I'm just going to use inplace is True to
actually update our DataFrame, so this
will be the version we will be working with from here.