So to detect the missing data in our
DataFrame, we use the function isnull,
which returns a Series that is true for
every cell that is not a number. And then
we can plug that into any, which returns
true if a column is true at least once. So
if we say df. isnull. any, we get an
overview of which columns have missing
values, or you can use the axis is 1
argument to show the rows that have
missing values. And then if you plug that
into an indexing, so here you see df.
float by square brackets, and then in the
square brackets the whole expression df.
isnull. any with axis is 1, this will
actually show you the contents of the rows
that have null values. Now there are two
other functions, notnull, which does
exactly the opposite of isnull, returns a
Series that's true for every cell that is
not null, and there's all that does the
opposite of any in the sense that it
returns true only if a column is
completely true. To remove parts of your
DataFrame, there's the function drop, and
of course you can use that function drop
to remove missing values as well. But
there's a more powerful function called
dropna, and this is actually a workhorse,
it can do a lot of things. First of all,
if you just call it like that, df. dropna,
it will drop all rows with null values
from your DataFrame. Or if you call it
with axis=1, it will drop all columns that
contain null values. Sometimes you only
want to drop those rows that have a lot of
missing values, and for that you can add
the argument thresh, which only keeps
those rows which have more values than the
threshold you specify. Then there's the
how argument, which lets you either drop
all the rows which are completely null, or
all the rows where one or more values are
null. So you can say how is all or how is
any. And finally, of course, there's the
inplace option which we've seen with
almost every function that you can use on
your DataFrame. Filling missing values you
do with the fillna method, and you can
just pass it the value and it will replace
all the null values in your DataFrame with
that value, so here it will replace all
the null values with the value 5. But
fillna can also accept a Series, and in
that case, you can, for example, compute
the mean for every column with df. mean,
pass that to fillna, and per column all
the nulls in each column will then be
replaced by the mean for that column. And
you can see that this is a very powerful
way to fill missing values with a
statistical estimate. Sometimes you want
to fill the null values with values based
on the surrounding data, and there's two
ways to do this. You can either use the
fillna method and you can give it a method
argument that tells it how to fill the
null values. Either give it the ffill
option, which fills forward, so when it
sees a null value it will fill that with
the previous value it has seen, or bfill
to fill backwards, which means if it sees
a null value it will take the next value
that it sees and fills backwards. Now of
course fillna also accepts the options
inplace and columns, as we've seen so far
with every other method. Now if you need a
little bit more advanced interpolation
where you do calculations based upon the
surrounding data, there's the df.
interpolate method which lets you do all
kinds of mathematic estimates for interpolating your data.