So we've either removed or filled all the
missing cells in our DataFrame, but there
might still be other unwanted values in
our DataFrame. Let's look at two classes
of unwanted values, outliers and
duplicates. There's not really something
like a formal definition of what exactly
an outlier is, but let's take a short look
of ways to detect and remove them anyway.
First of all, I'm reading in a dataset
about athletes who competed in the Olympic
games of 2016. And here we see the various
columns in our data. There are actually
some missing values in some of the
columns, but nothing to worry about right
now. For a visual indication of what our
data looks like, let's start with a small
scatterplot. First I need to say
matplotlib inline to make sure that the
notebook will show our plots. Then I type
athletes. plot. scatter and I select the
height column for the x axis and the
weight column for the y axis. And here we
see heights and weights of all the
athletes in the dataset plotted against
each other. You might say that there's
some kind of cluster of data points, and
there are some athletes that are not part
of that cluster. Now suppose I want to
filter out those athletes that are either
very tall, or not tall at all. I get the
height column from our DataFrame and store
it by itself into a new variable, heights.
This I can upload as a box plot by saying
heights. plot. box, and this gives a nice
visual representation of the distribution
of the heights. Half of all athletes are
within the box, and 25% of them are below
the box, and another 25 are above it. The
circles represent outliers. Now exactly
how an outlier is defined can differ
between box plots. The default behavior
for this plot is that it takes the edges
of the box, adds the total length of the
box times one and a half, and anything
further out than that is called an
outlier. Of course, this is kind of an
arbitrary definition of an outlier, and
since there are quite a lot of circles
here, it may not be the right definition
for this dataset exactly, but let's just
see if we can remove these outliers from
our dataset. I start by defining two
variables, q1 and q3, which are the first
and third quartile, or in other words the
25th and 75th percentile. If these terms
mean nothing to you, let me put it this
way, if we sort all heights in order from
short to tall, q1 here would be the data
point where exactly one fourth of all data
points are smaller, and q3 is the point
that has exactly three-quarters of all
data points smaller than it. And I'm
setting these values because they are
exactly the edges of the box on the box
plot. Saying q3 - q1 in the next line
gives us the height of the box, also known
as the interquartile range, or IQR. Very
well, now we can calculate the position of
the ends of the whiskers like this. Pmin
is the first quartile, minus 1. 5 times
the iqr, and pmax is the third quartile
plus 1. 5 times iqr. So now we have
basically the same data that the box plot
shows graphically. Pmin and pmax are the
horizontal lines at the end of the
vertical lines and everything beyond them
are outliers. So we can use this to remove
everything lying outside of the range pmin
to pmax. And because I will be throwing
data away, I prefer not to change my
original data at first. So let's make a
new variable, let's say nwh for new
heights, and here I select all data points
from heights between pmin and pmax. The
function between returns a series of
Booleans that is true whenever a value
lies between pmin and pmax. So I use this
series to index into the heights variable,
and this leaves me with a list of heights
that does not include outliers. This I
store in a variable, new heights. But
actually, let's think about this a moment.
Do I really want to remove the data points
with heights that are outside this range?
If I'm going to remove entire rows from
the DataFrame, I'll be throwing away other
data for these athletes too, like the
medals they've won for example, and this
might affect our results later on in a bad
way, so in this case I think it's better
to actually replace the outliers with null
values, so actually I'll be introducing
empty values in our dataset right now. And
one way to do this is by using the
function where. Now this method works a
little bit like an indexing operator in
the sense that I can pass it a list of
Booleans, which I do by using heights.
between as its first argument, and it
returns the original height for every true
element and null for every false element.
In other words, where replaces everything
that doesn't fall in the range pmin/pmax
with not a number. Now let me just repeat
that I'm not trying to tell you that this
is the way to remove outliers from your
data. What you consider an outlier will
depend on your data and what you want to
do with that data. For example, instead of
the code here you may want to write code
that selects everything outside of two
standard deviations around the mean, or
maybe you want to replace them with some
value, let's say the mean of all heights,
and in this case, you can add another
argument to the where function and this
will replace the outliers with the mean.
Now in my case it doesn't really make
sense to give a lot of people an average
height so let's just remove this again and
just replace the the outliers with null
values. So now I have two series, one with
outliers and one without, and I'd like to
compare them. A nice way to do this is to
put them side by side in a new DataFrame,
so I call pd. dataframe and pass it a
dictionary with the keys before and after,
and our two series as arguments. Now let's
compare these both in text and
graphically. So I'm going to say compare.
describe, and compare. plot. box. And now
we see a comparison of the data before and
after removing outliers. We've removed
about 100 data points, and this has
resulted in a slightly different mean
value and a tighter standard deviation.
The box plot, as well, shows that the
distribution of our data has hardly
changed, but all the circles are now gone.
Let's apply this to the original DataFrame
with athletes. I'll just copy the line
where I replaced the outliers with null,
and add inplace is true. Now if we draw
another scatterplot, this shows us that the data is now a bit more compact.