There is a third kind of unwanted data you
may have in your dataset, and that is
duplicate values. These may occur in your
data for any number of reasons, and right
now I'm going to show you how to get rid
of them. First of all, there's a function
called duplicated, which returns a list of
Boolean values. For each row it will
contain True if it's a duplicate and False
otherwise. Just running it like this tells
us nothing, but fortunately we can use the
any function to see if there are any
duplicate rows in our data, and it seems
that there are. So let's check them out by
using the call to duplicated to index our
DataFrame. So it seems that there's a
total of five rows that are duplicated, so
these rows appear more than once in our
data, and we can simply remove them with
another function called drop_duplicates.
And because I want to update my data
structure, I'll add inplace is True. And
now just to check, let's rerun this line.
There are no more duplicates in the set.
Now the drop_duplicates function has more
uses than just cleaning up a dataset with
unwanted duplicates. Sometimes it's a nice
tool for data exploration, for example, I
might want to know the list of countries
that has taken place in this tournament.
But since most countries send more than
one athlete, each country appears multiple
times in the list, but if I take the
column with nationalities and apply
drop_duplicates, we get a long list of 207
nationalities in the tournament. Of
course, you could also call sort_values on
this series to get the countries sorted by
name. But a lot of the time in scenarios
like these there's another function I like
to use instead of drop_duplicates, and
that is value_counts. This also returns
every value in the column once, but it
also counts how many times each value
occurs, so here we can see the same 207
nationalities, but we can immediately see
which countries sent the most athletes,
the USA followed by Brazil and Germany. Or
if we want to know the ratio of women
versus men, I can get the value_counts for
the sex column, and we see that the ratio
of men to women is about 6 to 5. We've
seen that the duplicated method returns a
series of Booleans that's true whenever a
row has been seen before, so when it's a
duplicate, and you can use this series, as
always, to index into your DataFrame. So
here we say df followed by square
brackets, and then inside the square
brackets we call df. duplicated, and this
will show you all the rows that are
actually duplicates. Now to remove all
duplicates, there's a separate function
called df. drop_duplicates, and this will
remove all duplicated rows from your
DataFrame. Interestingly, a DataFrame also
has another method called unique which has
the same behavior, but it doesn't return a
new DataFrame, it returns a numpy array,
so that means that most of the time you
don't want to use it, you just want to use drop_duplicates.