Now for the final part of this module,
let's look at two more ways to clean up
our data. First of all, let's convert
those values that have the wrong data type
into the right data type, and let's see
how we can tidy up our indices. So we've
done some cleanup of this dataset, but
looking at the output of athletes. info, I
see something I don't really like. Most
columns have type object, and this
basically means that they have been read
from the csv file as strings, and I don't
really agree with that. For example, let's
look at the three last columns.
Apparently, these cells denote the number
of medals an athlete won. In this case, we
see that the third athlete in our dataset
won a bronze medal, so these columns are
numbers. Why were they not read as
numbers? You see, when they're not seen as
numbers by Pandas, a lot of calculations
won't work the way we want them to. For
example, summing the bronze column to get
the total number of bronze medals awarded,
this just concatenates all the strings and
gives me a long list of ones and zeros,
and this is not really helpful, so let's
try to convert one of these columns to
integers and see what happens. And for
this there's the Pandas function astype.
Now this gives an error, and when I scroll
down all the way to the end we see that it
tells us that there's an invalid literal
for int. In other words, there's a value
in the data that cannot be converted to an
integer, and actually it turns out that
this is the capital letter O. So this data
was probably entered manually and someone
typed an O instead of a zero. So let's fix
this. I will retrieve the row holding this
value. So this row we see here holds O's
for the medals. I can change these values
into zeros, let me just copy the row
number here, and we'll use loc to retrieve
the row and select the three columns. And
I can just set them to 0. So let's try
again to convert these values into
integers. This time I'll try to convert
them all at once by just selecting all
three columns and saying. astype(int). And
let's assign the result back to the
original three columns. So I'm just going
to copy this here and assign that back
into itself. So now these columns should
contain integers, and we should be able to
do things like sum them to see how many of
each medal were given out. And that looks
a lot better. So now when I run athletes.
info again, here there's only one data
type left that I disagree with. If you
look in the csv file, you will see that
all the weights are given in whole
kilograms, so why do these show up here as
floats? Well, in this case it's because
some of these weights are missing, and the
only data types that can contain null
values in a DataFrame are either floats or
objects. So if you want to convert the
weights to ints, we either have to drop
the null values or fill them with some
integer value. And personally, in this
case I think both of these options don't
really make sense, so that means that I'll
have to live with a column that shows
floating points even though the source
values in the csv were integers. Now
unfortunately this is just one of the
limitations of Pandas. It's not possible
to have a column of integers that also contains empty values.