Let's do some final cleanup by cleaning
the index of our dataset. As it turns out,
the original csv data already contains an
id for each athlete, so why not just use
that for the index. We can do this by
assigning this column to the property
athletes. index. Now the only thing is
that the id column is now still here, so
now we have the id data twice. You can, of
course, just drop the id column, but
another approach is to not set the index
directly, but use the set_index function.
So here I say that I want to use the
contents of the id column for the index,
and after that please drop the id column
and let's do this inplace as well. So now
we have the athletes' id's as indices, and
the id column is gone. Now let's say I
want to change some column names as well.
I can do this with the rename function,
which lets me change column names using a
dictionary. So let's change the name of
the nationality column into the name
country, and instead of sport we'll use
the word discipline. And again, let's see
the results. So this lets us change the
labels on one or more columns. And you can
use this function on the rows as well, but
then the name of the first argument should
be index instead of columns. As a final
example, I want to take a moment to look
at the weather dataset. Let me just read
it in again, and let's just suppose I drop
all rows with null values. And because in
the original data only a small number of
rows contained no empty values at all, we
only have 831 rows left, so I just threw
away the majority of my data, but the
index, as you can see, still goes from 5
to 8783. Taking a look at the actual data,
you can see the gaps in the indices. Now
we can easily fix this by calling
reset_index, and this resets the index to
a simple range counting from 0 to the end
of the DataFrame. One side effect of this
is that the old index is stored in a new
column called Index, as you can see.
Sometimes that's nice to have, but right
now I just want to get rid of the old
index so I add an a argument drop is True,
and now we have our DataFrame with a nice continuously increasing index.