To convert the type of a Pandas column, we
can use the astype function, and we pass
it the date type we want to convert to. So
in this example here we take a column, in
this case we take the column called
some_column, and we call. astype(int) on
it to convert all the values to ints.
Alternatively, you can convert multiple
columns into different data types by
passing a dict into astype. So here I call
astype on the DataFrame as a whole by
saying df. astype, and I pass it a
dictionary that says I want to convert the
name column to a string and the age column
to an int. Now it's very important to
realize that all of this only works if all
values in the column actually fit into the
target data type. So let's say that the
age column in this example has only one
value that's not convertible to an int,
let's say it contains a character. In that
case, the df. astype will raise an
exception. So you'll have to make sure
that all your values actually conform to
the new data type before you try to call
astype. Now what kind of data types can
you pass to astype? Well, there's four
broad categories you have to be aware of.
First of all, there's strings. These are
nullable, so these cells can be empty, and
the string data type can be denoted in two
ways, you can just say str, which means
the Python string data type, or you can
say np. object. It doesn't really matter
which of these two you pass to the astype
method, because in any case the type of
your column will be objects, but it's good
to realize that in a sense these are
similar to Python strings. Then there's
floats. These are also nullable, so these
cells can also be empty, and you can use
the Python float data type, or in numpy
you can say np. float64. Actually, there
are some more numpy float data types, they
are, for example, float32, but normally
you won't need those, and the use of those
I consider to be a little bit too advanced
for this course. Then there's integers.
Integers cannot be null, they cannot be
empty, and as you probably know, integers
are whole numbers and floats are numbers
with a dot and a decimal part behind the
dot. Now for an integer you say either
int, which is the Python int data type, or
you use the numpy name, np. int64. And,
again, there's multiple numpy int data
types. There's also, for example, an
int32, and similarly as with float.
Usually you don't need it, you just use
np. int64. Now if you convert a column to
float and then you call info on your
DataFrame, you will see that the column is
of type float64. And similar with int, if
you say astype(int) usually you will see
that the column will be of type int64. And
then there's some other data types as
well. I don't really use those a lot in
this course, but I just want to mention
them here. For example, there's the bool
data type that can just be true or false,
and you can convert to that by saying
astype(bool), and there's the complex data
type for complex numbers, and those are
the four most important data types that
you might pass to the astype function. So
suppose you have a dataset and initially
it has a very nice index that has a range
of numbers counting from 0 up to the end
of the DataFrame, but you remove some rows
and after that your index is kind of
messed up, it's not continuous anymore. To
fix it, you call df. reset_index, and it
resets the index to a simple range. Now as
a side effect reset_index creates a new
column that has the data from the original
index, and in many cases you don't really
want that and you can add the drop is True
argument, and that will drop the original
index and you'll only be left with the new
index. Something else that sometimes
happens is that you read in a dataset and
it already has a column with data that you
would like to use for the index, and to do
that, you call set_index. So here I say
df. set_index, and as a first argument I
pass it the name of the column that I want
to use for my index. So in this case, the
column is named id, and I take all the
values from the id column to fill my
index. And, again, here we see the drop is
True argument to drop the original column
from our dataset so that we don't have the
same data twice. And the final thing we
saw is the rename method, and this lets me
rename either columns or indices by
passing a dictionary that contains the
original name and the new name for either
each column or each row. So in the first
example here I say rename with columns and
then I pass a dictionary and I rename the
column with name 'a' to Ann and the column
with name 'b' to Bob. And then in the
second argument I'm renaming rows. So here
I say index, which means the labels in the
indexes, and the row with index 'a' I
rename to Ann and the row with index 'b' I
rename to Bob. And that brings us to the
end of our module. What have we seen?
Well, we started by looking at missing
data. We learned how to find the missing
data in our dataset, and how to inspect
it. Then we saw how to remove it with the
dropna method or if we don't want to
remove it we can fill it with other values
based on the data in our DataFrame. For
this we saw two methods, fillna or
interpolate. Next we saw two other types
of unwanted data, outliers, for which it's
very hard to give a general way to remove
those, but I showed you some pointers of
how to find and remove outliers, and then
we looked at duplicates, for which there's
also some very nice Pandas methods like
drop_duplicates. Then we looked at type
conversions with the astype method, which
allows us to convert the type of data for
a column into another data type. And
finally, we saw how to tidy up our
indexes, either make them continuous again
or to set them based on the data in one of
our columns. And that's all I have to say
about cleaning data. I hope I'll see you
back in the next module, in which we'll
learn how to transform our data in a lot of different ways.