Hi, welcome to the last module of this
course, in which we'll see how to
transform our data into something
different. So you have a dataset, you've
cleaned it up, let's look at some things
we can do with our data. First of all,
let's do some calculations. We'll see how
to apply the basic math operators and how
to apply mathematical functions. We'll
also see how to define our own functions
and apply those to our data. After that,
we'll look at groupby, which is a very
powerful feature in Pandas that allows us
to split up our data into groups, apply
functions to those groups, and then
aggregate the results into a new
DataFrame. Now this might sound a little
bit abstract right now, but trust me, this
is a really powerful and cool feature in
Pandas. Then we'll move on to Pandas
operations that don't change the values of
your data, but the structure of your data.
A lot of the time when you receive a
dataset it doesn't have the structure you
want. In this part of the module, we'll
see several ways to restructure your data
either from rows to columns, or
vice-versa. Finally, we'll see several techniques to combine multiple datasets.