So let's start with our first demo in
which we'll see how to apply basic math
operations, and how to apply functions,
and we'll look both at mathematical
functions from the numpy library and
functions that we wrote ourselves. As
always, I start by importing numpy in
Pandas, and here I'm creating a new
DataFrame with five rows and four columns,
and it only contains ones, and I create
this using the numpy function ones. And I
set the names of the columns to a list of
characters, a, b, c, d. Now the mast basic
thing you can probably do is apply a basic
mathematical operator to the entire
DataFrame, so let's say, for example,
multiplying the entire DataFrame by 2. And
this multiplies every cell in the
DataFrame by 2. Now this doesn't update
the DataFrame itself, so if you want to do
that we have to use an equals sign here.
And then to display the DataFrame I have
to say df again. So after executing these
two lines, we see that the DataFrame now
contains the value 2 for every cell. We
can also use these operations on single
rows or cells. So, for example, I can
select a row with loc and divide it by 2,
or I can select a column and subtract 1.
And here you see that only the column and
the row we have selected have been
changed. Now this is all very
straightforward, but I can use these
mathematical operations on more complex
data types as well, so let's see what
happens if we use one of these operations
on two DataFrames instead of a DataFrame
and just a number. So to do that, of
course, I have to start by creating a new
DataFrame. So here I have a DataFrame,
again, with only ones in it, and it has
three rows and two columns, and the
columns in this case are called d and e,
and the rows are 2, 4, and 5, so we have a
non-continuous index here. Now let's see
what happens if I try to add this second
DataFrame to the first DataFrame by saying
df + df2. And the result here may surprise
you. We get a lot of not a numbers, and we
get only two values. So how does this
work? Well, first of all it's important to
realize that Pandas always works in terms
of indices and labels. Now when I add two
DataFrames it will take every position in
the first DataFrame and try to find the
same position in the second DataFrame and
add those. So scrolling up a bit, the
first cell in df1 has column a and row 0.
Pandas will try to locate a cell in df2
that has row 0 and column a as well. Now,
as you can see in df2, there's no such
thing, there is no column a, and there's
also no row 0, but in the output we do see
a column a and a row 0. So basically,
Pandas takes every row and every column
from both DataFrames, and puts them all in
the output. So the columns a, b, c, d were
all in our first DataFrame, so they all
show up in the output, but column e is
only in DataFrame 2 and it still shows up
in the output. And then the actual
calculation is only executed for those
cells that are in both DataFrames. And in
this example there's only two cells that
overlap. Again, scrolling up, there's a d2
in DataFrame 1 and there's a d2 in
DataFrame 2, so these values we can now
add, So that's 2 + 1 is 3. Let's look at
the output, and we see the result in cell
d2 is 3. Similarly, there's a d4 in both
DataFrames. Those get added and the result
shows up in the output. So basically, what
happens is that Pandas takes what we call
the Cartesian product of all the rows and
columns, so basically there will be a row
for every row index in both of the inputs,
and there will be a column for all the
column labels in both of the inputs. Now
for every combination of a row and column
that doesn't contain a value for both
inputs, we get NaN, as you see here. Now
the second question is, what will happen
if I use a mathematical operation on two
Series. So let's take a row from both
DataFrames, and basically here we see the
same thing. There's five values here, one
for every column from each of the inputs,
so a, b, c, d come from our first
DataFrame, and the e column is added by
our second DataFrame, and again, we only
see a result for the case where there's a
value in both inputs, and in all other
cases the result is NaN. And then, of
course, there's the question of operating
on a DataFrame in a series, and the
classical example for this is removing the
mean from your columns. As you may
remember, the mean of a DataFrame returns
the mean value for every column. So here
we have a Series that has a value for each
column, and that means that when I say df
- df. mean, I'm subtracting a Series from
a DataFrame. And this probably does what
you would expect it to do. For every
column it takes the corresponding value
from the Series and subtracts it from each
of its cells. So for column a we take the
a value from our df. mean series and
subtract it from each cell in column a,
and for the b column we take the b value
from df. mean and subtract it from every
cell in b, etc., etc. Now here I have a
different example of subtracting a Series
from a DataFrame. I'm creating a series
that has four values, but in this case the
labels of the values are a, b, e, and f,
so the labels don't completely correspond
with the column names of our DataFrame.
When I execute this, we see that the same
thing happens as we saw before when we
tried to add two DataFrames. For every
column label that isn't in both of the
inputs, we get NaN. Now what if I want to
apply one of these operations on the rows
instead of the columns, so I want to take
the mean for every row and then subtract
it from every row? Well we know that to
take the mean for every row we can say df.
mean with axis=1, but if I try to subtract
this from my DataFrame, I get a result
with only null values in this. This is
because my df. mean works per row, so the
indices of my df. mean are the index
labels for my rows, which is 0, 1, 2, 3,
4, and these are different from the column
labels. So subtraction like this only
works per column. If we wanted to work
over the other axis, I have to use
different methods. I have to say df. sub.
So df. sub is a DataFrame method that does
subtraction and basically it does the same
as the minus symbol, but it gives us some
more options. So here, for example, I can
give an axis argument, and this allows me
to subtract the mean row-wise for every row for my DataFrame.