So we've seen how we can apply simple
mathematical operations, but what if you
want to do some more complex mathematics?
Well, let me show you some examples. First
of all, here I'm creating a DataFrame, and
I'm adding two columns, sin and cos. And
the sin column I fill with values from 0
to 5 pi with a step size of 0 to 0. 01,
and the cos column I fill similarly, but
here I start at 0. 5 times pi and I go all
the way up to 5. 5 times pi. Now right now
this DataFrame contains simply a range of
numbers that counts from 0 upwards. Now
let's apply a function to this. I want to
apply the sin function to each cell in my
DataFrame. Now numpy already has these
kinds of functions for us, so numpy offers
a very complete set of mathematical
operations we can apply to our data. So in
this case I can simply say np. sin. df. So
np. sin is what numpy calls a universal
function, and this is the kind of function
that we can simply apply to our DataFrame
and it will calculate the sin for every
single value in our DataFrame. Now to show
you the results, let's immediately plot
it. Of course, I have to say matplotlib
inline to actually show the plots, and
then I say df. plots. So here we can see
that all the values I generated at first
have now had the sin function applied to
them, and this gives us this beautiful
graph here. Now as I just said, numpy is
very complete and it contains functions
for just about everything, not just
trigonometry, but exponentials,
logarithms, etc., etc. So that's very nice
if you want to use a well-known standard
mathematical function, but what if you
have a function that you wrote yourself
that you want to apply to your data? As an
example here, I wrote a function iqr that
takes a column from a DataFrame as input,
and it calculates the interquartile range.
Now, if you don't know what that means, it
doesn't really matter, the point here is I
wrote a function that works on a column of
a DataFrame, and to apply this to my
DataFrame I can simply say df. apply iqr.
And here I don't use parentheses, because
if I would use parentheses here like this
I would be calling my function, and that's
not what I want to do. I want to pass the
function to df. apply, and then df. apply
will call the function for me on each
column in my DataFrame. So now by
executing this I apply my iqr function to
each of the columns in my DataFrame, and
it returns these two values here. Now, of
course, you can also apply a function to
each of the rows, and in that case you add
the axis=1 argument. Now there's a lot of
rows here, and they all contain only two
values, so this doesn't really make sense,
so let's remove this. Very well. Now what
if you wrote a function that you don't
want to apply to a column, but you want to
apply it to every single value in your
DataFrame? So here I wrote a very simple
function. It takes a value, x, adds. 25 to
it, and then calculates the absolute value
of that, and I want to apply this function
to every single cell in my DataFrame. Now
I cannot use the apply method because it
works for rows or columns. Now to apply a
function to every cell, you say df.
applymap, and again, you pass the name of
your function. And don't forget, no
parentheses here, because, again, we want
applymap to apply the function for us, so
we're not going to run the function right
here. Now I'm just going to plot this
immediately so we can see the output. So
this has applied my somefunc function to
every single cell in my DataFrame, and here we see the result.