So let's go over what we've just seen.
First of all, here's an example of using a
binary operator with two Series. In this
case I'm using the plus operator, and as
you can see, the first Series has indices
a, b, c, and the second Series has indices
b, e, and the result of adding these two
together is a new Series object that
contains all of the indices from both
inputs. Now, the one green row here has
the index b, and this is the only index
that is contained in both of the inputs.
That's why I made it green in the output
because it's the only one that actually
has a result. All the other rows, a, c,
and e have as an output value NaN. So, the
general rule is that the results will only
be filled for those indices that are in
both inputs. In all other rows, the result
will be NaN. Here we see a similar
example, but I'm multiplying two
DataFrames. The rules are more or less the
same though. So I've used colors here to
make it a little bit more clear what part
of the results come from which input. So,
for example, column a in the output is
blue because it comes from the first
input, but because the second input
doesn't have column a, all the values in
the output in column a will be NaN. And,
again, in this example there's only one
cell that actually contains a value, and
that's cell b1. This is, of course,
because both the first and the second
input have a column b and a row 1. Now
this is the third example, and here we're
operating on a DataFrame and a Series, and
in this case it works a little bit
differently. Now what I like to do in this
case, I like to rotate the Series in my
mind so that it's horizontal instead of
vertical. You see, in this operation the
indices of my series are matched on the
column labels of my DataFrame. You can
also see this in the output. There's a
column a in the output, and that comes
from the first label a from my Series. Now
these kinds of operations are executed per
row of my DataFrame. So we take the first
row of my DataFrame, apply the operation
with our Series, and that becomes the
first row of my results. Then we take the
second row of the DataFrame, apply the
operation with the Series again, and that
becomes the second row, etc., etc. Now
what if you want to apply a mathematical
operation on a DataFrame and a Series, but
you want to apply the Series to every
column instead of every row? Well, that's
not possible with the normal mathematical
operators, so for those cases Pandas gives
us a set of functions. All of these
support the axis argument so you can tell
them to operate on the columns instead of
the rows. There's df. add if you want to
add a Series to your DataFrame, and
there's df. radd if you want this, but you
need your DataFrame to be on the
right-hand side of the operator.
Similarly, there's df. sub for subtracting
something from your DataFrame, and there's
df. rsub if you want your DataFrame to be
on the right-hand side of the minus sign.
There's mul and rmul for multiplication,
and div and rdiv for division. There's
also floordiv and rfloordiv for Python
floor division, and finally there's
functions for powers and the modulo
function. Numpy offers us a large number
of mathematical functions that we can
apply directly on our DataFrame or Series,
and in numpy these functions are called
ufuncs, for universal functions. So here
in the example you see np. sin for
computing the sin function and np. exp for
computing the exponential function. Now
for a complete list of the ufuncs that
numpy has to offer, here's a link to the
numpy documentation. Now if you wrote a
function yourself that you want to apply
to your data, or maybe there's a function
from a different library that you want to
apply, there's the df. applymap function.
And what you do is you pass your function
to df. applymap, but you don't put
parentheses after your function name. So
this way you pass the function as an
object to applymap, and it will call
applymap for every cell in your DataFrame,
and this will return a new DataFrame with
the results. Now, an important thing to
realize is that you can also do this on a
Series object, but in that case the method
on the Series is called apply and not
applymap. And to make things a little bit
more confusing, a DataFrame also has an
apply method and you can also pass a
function to it, but this will apply the
function to every column of your DataFrame
or to every row of your DataFrame. So
DataFrame. apply and Series. apply have
the same name, but they do different
things, because Series. apply applies a
function to every value in every cell of
the Series, whereas DataFrame. apply
applies a function to whole rows and
columns. Now the first two examples here
show you how to apply a function for every
column of your DataFrame, and the third
example has the axis argument and this will make apply work for every row.