Let's take a look at grouping and
aggregation with groupby, which is one of
the coolest and most powerful features in
Pandas. So let's take a look at a very
powerful mechanism in Pandas called
groupby. And to show you a demo, here we
have the athletes dataset, which we're now
familiar with, and I cleaned it up a
little bit so there won't be any problems
with duplicates or having the wrong data
types or any of that. Now what groupby
lets us do is it lets us break down our
dataset into groups and then apply
calculations to these groups. Let's just
dive straight into an example. If I say
athletes. groupby nationality, this
returns me a DataFrameGroupBy object, and
this by itself tells me nothing. So let's
just assign this to a variable g, and I'm
going to say g. sum, and this returns me a
new DataFrame. And in this DataFrame the
first thing that strikes me is that the
index is now nationalities. So what
groupby does is it takes our original
data, splits it up into groups by
nationality. So basically you can think of
the groupby object containing a set of
smaller DataFrames, each with one of our
nationalities. So it takes every value
from the nationality column and makes new
little DataFrames for each of the values
there. And then on these groups we can do
calculations. So here we see the sums of
all the ids for every athlete from
Afghanistan. Of course, this doesn't
really make sense, but that's what it
does. This is the sum of all their
heights, and this is the sum of all their
weights. And the same data is in here for
all my different nationalities. So
scrolling down, for example, here we see
the sums of heights and weights for
Belgium. Of course, the most interesting
thing here is the sum of the medals, so
how many gold medals and silver medals did
a country win. And since g. sum here is a
DataFrame, of course I can ask for these
columns here. So I can select just a set
of columns for my DataFrame. But actually
it's smarter to do this on the groupby
object, so I'm just going to move this
selection here to the place where I define
my groupby object. And why this is better?
Well, this selects the columns before I
start doing my calculations, so now the
sum will only be done for the three
columns that I'm asking about. Now let's
look at a different example. Let's group
our athletes by sport. Again, I'm
assigning the groupby object to the
variable g, and let's say I'm only
interested in weights for now. And on this
groupby object I can do different things
than just sum. Let's ask for the mean
weight. And in this case, because we only
selected a single column, I get a series
with the mean weight per sport for my
dataset. You know what, let's also select
the height, and in this case I get a nice
DataFrame. But apart from selecting
multiple columns, I can also select
multiple levels to groupby, so let's not
just group by sport, but also be gender.
So to do this, I pass to groupby a list,
so using square brackets again, with the
name of multiple columns I want to group
on. So here I first group by sport, and
then by sex. So let's again go over what
this actually does. Groupby takes our
DataFrame and makes nice little DataFrames
for every combination of sport and gender.
So it makes a DataFrame for female archery
players, and one for male archery players,
and one for female badminton players, and
one for male badminton players, etc., etc.
Then from there we select the weight and
height columns only, and after that when I
say g. mean, for every one of these
groupings we calculate the means of these
two columns. So then we have a mean,
again, for every female archery player,
and a mean for every male archery player,
etc., etc., and at the end, all of this
gets combined into this DataFrame you see here.