So let's visualize what happens when I do
a groupby. Let's take a look at this
DataFrame here. We have a number of
students, and we have a class column that
tells me per student in which class he or
she belongs. Now if I say df. groupby
class, this splits up my DataFrame into
groups per class. So internally the
groupby object will have groups of data
for my DataFrame. It doesn't really make
internal DataFrames, but it's a nice way
to think of it like that. Now the groupby
object at this point hasn't done any
calculations yet. It didn't even break up
my data into groups really. It only starts
doing real calculations when I call an
aggregation function on it, like g. mean.
At this point, it calculates means for all
the columns in each of the groups, and
then creates a new DataFrame out of that.
So this results in a DataFrame with a row
for every group, and then in each row for
every column where we can calculate the
mean, you will see the means. Now, in many
cases you're only interested in the data
in some of your columns, and the best
thing to do here is to select these
columns immediately when you make your
groupby object. So like in the example
here, I call groupby and immediately after
the call to groupby I already select the
columns I'm interested in. So here I say
groupby sport and I select only the gold
column, and this will cause groupby to
only do calculations for that column. So
then when I say. sum, only the sums for
the gold column will be calculated. You
can also groupby multiple columns. So the
second example here shows you a call to
groupby where I pass a list of columns,
and in this case I'm grouping by both
sport and nationality. Now if you do a
groupby operation where you group on
multiple columns, the result will have a
multi-level index, like the example shown
here. Now a multi-level index is something
I'm not talking about a lot in this
course, but the general concept is really
easy to understand. In this case we have
an index with two levels, sport and sex,
and first we see a value for the sport
index, boxing, and below that we see the
different values for the sex column,
female and male. Then we have another
value in the sport index, cycling, and
again below that we have the values for
the second level index, sex. So if you use
groupby and you select multiple columns,
you will get a multi-level index, and in a
moment we'll see some other operations
that either result in or use multi-level
indexes. Now what kind of functions can
you call on a groupby object? Well,
there's a number of functions that are a
part of the groupby class, and those are
optimized functions. You can see them
listed above here. They're functions like
count, sum, mean, min, max, and the
standard deviation, etc., etc. But you can
actually call all the functions on the
underlying object as well. So if you
groupby on a DataFrame, you can call all
DataFrame functions on your groupby
objects. Or you can use groupby to apply
to actually call a function you defined yourself on the groupby object.