So we've seen how we can transform our
data by applying functions to it, but
let's see how we can transform the
structure of our DataFrame. So we'll see
how to move our data from our columns to
our rows, or from our rows to our columns,
and there's four functions that are of
interest here, stack, unstack, pivot, and
melt. Sometimes you just don't agree with
the way your data is structured into rows
and columns. As an example, let's take
this dataset, monthly_data. csv, and here
it shows a row for every year, and then
the months are in the columns. So here for
2009 we have a value for January and one
for February, etc., etc., and then the
values for 2010 are on the next line. Now
this is vey nice, but what if I want to
see the chronological order of all these
values, let's say I want to plot how these
values change over time. Then it would
nicer if all these values are in a single
column. Now there's a function to do just
that, but before we do this let's remove
the year column and put it in the index.
So for that I have the set_index function,
as you may remember, and I use
inplace=True to immediately update our
DataFrame. So now we have the years as the
index, and then I can call the. stack
method, and this will move all the data
from my rows into a single column. Let me
show you. So now we have a Series that has
all our data points below each other. So
first we get the values for the first row,
and then for the second row, etc., etc.
Our values are indexed first by year, and
then inside the year they're indexed by
month. Now I'm not saying a lot in this
course about multi-level indexing, but we
have already seen them with groupby. So
groupby and stack are two typical
scenarios where you will see a multi-level
index. So after calling stack, it's also
suddenly possible to do calculations for
the entire dataset. So if I want to know
the sum of all my data, I can simply say
m. stack. sum. And because after stack all
my data will be in a single column,
calling sum on that column will give me
the sum of all my data. Now stack also has
a reverse called unstack, and that will
put my data from my columns into my rows.
As an example, let's look at what we saw
in the previous demo the mean weight of
athletes grouped by sport and gender. So
here we have a value for every combination
of sport and gender, and all these values
are below each other in a single column.
Now, as I just said, unstack will move
values from columns into rows. So here we
have a multi-level index, and the inner
level is our gender. So the first level is
the sport and the second level is the
gender, and unstack, by default, will take
the inner level of our index. So we will
get two columns, one for females and one
for males. So let's execute this and here
we see the same data, but instead of
everything being in a single column, it's now in two rows.