Now here's another scenario where I don't
like the way my data is structured. Now
I'm creating a DataFrame here, and
remember, I'm making this file available
for download so you don't have to type
along here, and the DataFrame here has
data about products sold in a store. And
as you can see, for every product id here
I have different lines, and then per line
I give some item. So here I have a product
where I have a price, a unit, and a stock.
Now although you do sometimes come across
data that is structured this way, it's not
really the way I like it, because in my
opinion, every product should be on its
own row, and then all its properties in
the columns. Of course, as always, Pandas
has a function for this. It's called
pivot. Now pivot is a little bit like
unstack in the sense that it moves my data
from columns into rows, so I will get a
new DataFrame that is both wider and
shorter because we will only have one row
per product. And as the first argument I
have to tell it what my row index will be.
So I'm going to say please take the id's
as row indices, so for every unique id we
will now get a row. And the second
argument will be where to get my column
names. So I'm going to say please take
your column names from the item column. So
this means I will now have columns prize,
unit, and stock. And as the third
argument, I can pass the column with which
to fill my DataFrame, so the one that
actually contains my values, and of
course, this is the value column. But
because the value column is also the only
column that is left after id and item, I
can also completely leave it out, so let's
just leave out this third argument. And
here we see our same product data again,
but now we can really clearly see that
there are exactly three products, and the
id's for the products are now in the
index. Then per item, price, stock, and
unit we now have three columns, and in
these columns, we have the data that was
previously in the value column. Now to see
the opposite of pivot, let's take a look
at the grades dataset. We've seen this
before. It lists test scores for students
in a classroom. Now in this case what I
want to do is quite similar to the stack
function. I want to move all my grades
into a single column, but I also want an
extra column that tells me from which
column the data came, so I want an extra
column that tells me per grade for which
test that grade was. So to do this I call
grades. melt. And then we see here all our
grades with a separate column that tells
us for which test they are. But the
problem here is that we now lost the
information about the students, so we
can't see for which student each grade is.
Let's fix this. First I'm going to call
grades. reset_index. And the result of
this is that now we have an index from 0
to 4, and the student names are now in a
column called index. So now if I call
grades. melt I get something unexpected.
Basically I get a single column with all
the values from my dataset, and it tells
me from which column they are. And this is
not exactly what I want, because I want
these names in a separate column. And to
fix this I can pass to melt a list of
columns that I want to use to identify
what values we have. So basically I say
here this index column with these names,
those are not just values, they are used
to identify what kind of value we have. So
the 6 here we see, we don't just want to
know that it's for test 1, we also want to
know that it's a grade for Mary. So here I
say id_vars is index, and note that this
is inside a list so there's square
brackets here, and then executing this now
we have the result I want. We see all our
values in a single column, we have a
column that contains the name for each
student for each grade, and we also have a
column that identifies the test for each grade.