Let's take a slightly more formal look at
how pivot works. Pivot transforms one
column of data into multiple different
columns. And you can give it three
arguments. The first one is the index
column, and you pass the name of a column
and for each unique value in that column
there will be an index for one of your
rows. The second argument is the name of a
column that you will use for the column
labels, so from that column it will take
unique values and for every unique value
there will be a column. And the third
argument is the column from where the data
will be taken. So a new DataFrame will be
constructed with rows for every value from
the first column, columns for every value
from the second column, and the values
will come from the third column. Now if
this is a little bit abstract, let's
visualize this. So here I have a DataFrame
with product id's, and then for every
product we have prices or stocks, and we
can know if the value in the value column
is a price or a stock by whatever is
listed in the item column. Now with pivot
I can convert this into a DataFrame where
I have one row for every product. To do
this, I say df. pivot, and as the first
argument I give the name of the prod_id
column. So this will take every unique
product id and make one row. And the
second argument is item, and this means
that for every unique value in the item
column there will be a column in the
output. So when I run this there's a new
DataFrame created, and as you can see, the
row labels 1, 2, and 3 are taken from the
prod_id column in the input. The column
names, price and stock, are from the item
column, and the values are taken and
filled in in the correct places. So the
price for product 1 is 11, and the stock
for product 2 is 2, etc., etc. The
opposite of pivot is melt. It moves data
from multiple columns into a single
column, and the most important argument
that you can give to melt is called
id_vars. Id_vars identifies the column
that contains id's in your dataset, so in
our previous example, this would be the
product id column. Now melt works by
taking all the values that are not in this
id_vars column, and puts them all in a
single column, and then it takes the
column labels from your original data and
puts these in a separate column under the
name variable. Now let's look at a little
visualization to make this a little bit
more clear. Let's take the same example as
with pivot, but let's work backwards. So
here I have the DataFrame that was the
result of our pivot operation a moment
ago. And in this case, before I can use
melt I want to move my index into one of
my columns, because in this case my index
contains my product id's, but melt only
looks at the data in my columns, so I want
to move my index into a column. So I start
by preparing the DataFrame, and I call df.
reset_index on it, so this moves my index
into a new column, index, and then I say.
rename and I rename the new index column
to prod_id. So this results in the
DataFrame on the right-hand side here. I
have a new index 0, 1, 2, which is simply
a range, and I have a new column, prod_id,
that contains the indices from the
original DataFrame. So now all the data I
want is in my columns, and I can call
melt. So now I say df. melt and I pass it
the id_vars argument, and I tell it that
my product id column contains the id's.
And you can see the result here on the
right-hand side. I now have a row for
every combination of a product id and a
price or a stock. So price and stock here
are values that are taken from the column
labels of our original DataFrame, and the
corresponding values are in the value
column. So now you can see that the price
for product 1 is 11, and the stock for
product 2 is 2, etc., etc. Another
function we saw is stack, and this is
quite similar to melt in that it moves
data from multiple columns into a single
column. The difference is that stack
simply puts all your data in a single
column and adds a multi-level index. So
now we have all our values below each
other, and we have a multi-level index
where the first level is our original
index, so the product id's, and the second
level tells us whether it's a price or a
stock. And, of course, stack also have an
opposite called unstack. This looks at
your innermost index level, so in this
case it's the index that says price or
stock, and for every unique value in this
index it contains a column. So in the
result we now have a column stock and a
column price, so as you can see, this is
exactly the opposite as the stack method from the previous slide.