And that brings us to our last demo. Let's
see how we can combine data from multiple
data structures. So here I have my
familiar grades dataset. Now let's say I
have a Series that contains the result
from a new test I took. So here I have a
Series with results for every student, and
to add this as a column I can simply
assign this to a new column, and this
simply adds the Series as a new column to
our DataFrame. So this is a familiar
scenario, and in a similar way we can add
a row to this DataFrame. In this case I
will use loc to do row-based indexing. So
let's add grades for a student called Bob.
Now in this case I can use a simple list
to create the new row, but this wouldn't
have worked for the column, because when I
add a column I need something that
contains indices, so I have to use a
Series. Now just like Python lists,
DataFrame also has an append method which
lets us append rows to the end of our
DataFrame. But when I pass a simple list
to it, it doesn't work as I expected. You
see, when I pass a list to append it
interprets every element of this list as a
single row, so it will add a row for the
value 5 and a row for the value 4, etc.,
etc. And because these elements don't have
indices, we get this strange result here
where there's a new column called 0, and
the new rows also have indices like 0, 1,
2, 3. Now to do this correctly, I actually
want a data structure that has indices, so
let's make a Series again. So here I've
created a new Series called new_row, and
it contains indices test_1, test_2,
test_3, test_4, so we should be able to
append this to my DataFrame. Let's see if
it works. But now I get an error. It says
it can only append a Series if
ignore_index is true or if the Series has
a name. Basically, Pandas wants to know
how to set the row_index for this new_row,
and the best way to do this is to actually
give our Series a name. So the name of
this Series will be used as the row_index.
So here I'll give it the name of a
student, Kim, and then if I append it, now
the grades for Kim have been appended to
my DataFrame. So that tells us how to add
single dimensional data to our DataFrame
in the sense of adding a row or a column,
but what if I want to combine multiple
DataFrames into one DataFrame? Well, to
show you that, I'm going to add student
numbers, so student id's to my DataFrame.
So here I'm creating a new column,
stud_nr, and I'm adding an id for every
student, and then in the second line here
I'm selecting the columns from my grades
DataFrame in a specific order. So this
lets me move the student number column to
the first position, because otherwise if I
wouldn't do this, then the student number
column would now be the last column in my
DataFrame, and I just think that's ugly.
Very well, so now we have grades, and
student numbers, and let's create a second
DataFrame that I want to merge with this
DataFrame. So here's a new DataFrame that
has a different set of student numbers and
two columns for two different exams. Now,
I want to combine all of this data into a
single new dataset, and for that there's
the merge method. If I call grades. merge
other, this is my result. I see columns
for all my tests and my exams so that
looks good, but why do I only see four
rows? Well, the answer is simple, grades.
merge, by default, does something we call
an inner join, and what that means is it
looks for a column that's present in both
inputs, so in this case that's the student
number column, and then it takes only
those values from that column that are
present in both inputs, so in this case
only the four students that we see here
were present in both inputs. Now merge
takes an extra argument, how, and that
lets me do different kinds of joins. So I
can do a left join by saying how is left,
and in that case I get a new DataFrame for
all the student numbers that were present
in my left input, so in the grades
DataFrame. And you can also see that in
the output now there are two students that
have NaN for the two exams from my new
DataFrame, because those two students are
not present in my new DataFrame.
Similarly, if I say how is right, I only
get the students that are present in my
second DataFrame, and here you can see
that the four tests are empty for my last
two students. Now there's also a final
option called an outer join, and this will
simply contain all the data from both
inputs. And that's the end of this course.
What have we seen in this module? Well, we
started by doing calculations on our data.
We saw basic math operations, we applied
mathematical functions, and we wrote our
own functions and applied those to our
DataFrames. Then we took a good look at
groupby and all the different kinds of
operations you can do with that. We saw
several ways to transform the structure of
a DataFrame by moving data from rows to
columns, or from columns to rows, and in
the last demo we saw how we can combine
multiple data structures into a single
DataFrame. Thank you for watching this
course. My name is Reindertjan Ekker for Pluralsight.